What is a Dockerfile? It is a plain text document containing sets of instructions for Docker
to build an image. This file will tell Docker how to build the image of our .NET app.
Dockerfile builds image in layers with each instruction creating a new layer. Let us now
understand the Dockerfile of our .NET app. There are stages and each starting from the
from instruction.
It gives each of these stage some named like base, build, publish and final.
See the first stage from mci.microsoft.com/dotnet/aspnet colon 10 references the .NET
10 runtime image which is a lightweight compared to SDK version. This stage is given the name base.
The dollar app underscore UID is an environment variable for non-root users that will be used to
run the command here. The work directory slash app creates a directory by the name of app in the
image of our .NET app. And it sets it as the working directory. It then exposes the container
port's number 8080 and 8081 to the outside world. That is to the host machine. So this way we can
access the container on these ports. Obviously one port will be for HTTP and the other for the
HTTPS versions. So we have our local machine on the left and it contains our .NET app with
Dockerfile and on the right here is the Docker image of our app. The first stage tells .NET app
image to reference the .NET runtime image from mci. It then creates a work directory called app
inside the image and exposes ports 8080 and 8081 of the container that will be containing this
image of our app. Let's now move to the second stage. Here will be restoring and building the app
using .NET restore and .NET build commands. So we have reference the SDK image of .NET 10 and
not its runtime image like before. The name this stage build argument build underscore configuration
is set to release. Then work directory slash src creates a new directory called src in the .NET
apps image. Inside this directory first docker app cs project file is copied from the local machine.
Now the .NET restore command is run for the cs project file which is inside the docker image
of the .NET app. This will restore the dependencies like NuGet packages and dls which the app has
after that with copy .NET command all the apps files are copied from the local machine to the src
directory on the image. The first dot is for the from location on the local machine
and the second dot is for the location on the image which is set to the work dir instruction.
Finally the .NET build command builds the apps cs project file inside the src directory.
In the build command configuration is set as release and output from this command will be placed
in the apps slash build directory inside the image. Let us understand this from the animations.
The src directory is first created inside the .NET apps image. Now the apps project file is copy
to this src directory from the local machine. Next we run the .NET restore command on this cs
project file. After that we copy all the apps files from the local machine to inside this src
directory. Finally we build this app cs project file and the output is placed inside the apps
slash build directory. Notice the dash O parameter given on the .NET build command. Moving to the
third stage where we publish the app by running the .NET publish command we reference the build
stage from build as publish. The .NET publish command is run on the cs project file of the app which
is residing on the src directory in the image. Build_configuration is kept as release and output
is set to app slash publish folder inside the image of the .NET app. The use app host property
is set to false. This will disable the creation of platform specific executable of the app.
This means it will be producing platform independent exc of the app. Let's see the animations to
understand this. We run .NET publish command on the cs project file located inside the src
directory and the output of this command goes to app slash published directory inside the image.
Here the app published files are kept. Final stage references the base stage.
Then work directory is set to app. After that the copy command is used to copy from publish stage
app slash publish directory to the app directory on the route. Finally the entry point instruction
specifies to run the dll called first docker app dot dll when the container starts.
In this way whenever the container starts our .NET app will start running.
So this is the slide of the final stage. It copies all the files from the app slash publish folder
to the app folder and adds entry point to the first docker app dot dll file. What is dot docker
ignore file? You will find it below the docker file. Click the arrow in front of the docker file
to open the dot docker ignore file. This file lists the files and folders directories to exclude
from the building context of the image. There are matching patterns given per line example
asterisk asterisk means to match anything. So asterisk asterisk dot class path means to ignore files
that are of dot class path extension. And residing on the local machine the exclamation pattern
is to re include the files and directories that are excluded by the previous pattern.
So this means these patterns will be included. Example the dot get ignore file will be included
similarly for the others.